Finding Aid for Ernest L. Cooley Papers, 1875-1928
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ernest L. Cooley Papers 1875-1928
Cooley, Ernest Linwood, 1856-1928.
5 linear ft.
Chicago, Illinois engineer. Personal and business papers, notes, reports, and correspondence, much of it with his brother Mortimer E. Cooley and Chase S. Osborn; include material concerning the Cooley family genealogy, water engineering projects, the Hudson Bay Co., 1850-1908, the St. Lawrence Seaway, and Mortimer E. Cooley's race for the U.S. Senate in 1924.
85984 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278 )
The collection is open for research.
Ernest L. Cooley was a civil and hydraulic engineer. In 1895, he became affiliated with the Sanitary District of Chicago where he worked until his death in 1928. His work here had to do with the hydraulic design of channels, sewers, dams, and special structures of the District.
The Ernest L. Cooley papers consist of correspondence, engineering reports and notes, and Cooley family genealogical material. Included is an extensive exchange of correspondence with his brother Mortimer E. Cooley, dean of the Engineering School of The University of Michigan. These letters concern vacation plans for trips to northern Michigan and Canada, and Mortimer Cooley's candidacy for the U.S. Senate from Michigan in 1924 (especially correspondence, July 1924 to Jan. 1925). There is also material relating to the management of the Cooley farm in Georgia 1927; the controversy surrounding the falling level of the Great Lakes (i.e., Nov. 18, 1926); and other engineering projects.
Another of his correspondents was Chase S. Osborn, former governor of Michigan. These letters cover personal matters growing out of their retreats to Osborn's summer camp at Duck Island. There is also material relating to the proposed St. Lawrence Waterways in letters of Aug. 1927 and throughout. Other than correspondence, the collection includes reports made on hydraulic engineering projects, particularly relating to flood control in the Chicago area, and the diversion of the Des Plaines River. Cooley also collected material relating to the history of the Hudson Bay Company. There are several folders of original business correspondence, reports, and accounts of the Hudson's Bay Company, 1850-1908. Miscellaneous items of interest include Cooley family genealogy found particularly in correspondence of 1915-1916. Cooley also wrote a short autobiographical sketch, Dec. 30, 1920; there is also a note on William Randolph Hearst, June 20, 1912.
Subjects:
Chicago (Ill.); Cooley, Ernest Linwood, 1856-1928.; Engineers--Illinois--Chicago.; Hudson's Bay Company.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Saint Lawrence Seaway.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1924.; United States--Politics and government--1923-1929.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Camping.; Canoes.; Chicago and Alton Railroad Company.; Chicago Sanitary District.; Cooley, Ernest Linwood, 1856-1928.; Offices--Illinois--Chicago.; Railroads--Illinois.; Recreation.
Contributors:
Cooley, Lyman Edgar, 1850-1917.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Cooley family.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated and 1875-June 1912, 48 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1912-March 1919, 41 folders (Box 2)
  - April 1919-1928, 45 folders (Box 3)
  - With Chase S. Osborn concerning the St. Lawrence Seaway, 1927 (Box 3)
- Genealogical Materials
  - Cooley family (Box 3)
  - Griswold family (Box 3)
  - Miscellaenous (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Professional Papers
  - Artesan Water Co., reports concerning, undated (Box 4)
  - Notes concerning the Chicago River, undated (Box 4)
  - Chicago Sanitary District reports, 1917-1924, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 16 folders (Box 4)
  - Notes and writings, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Hudson Bay Company file, 1857-1908, 26 folders (Box 5)
    (lacking papers for 1860-1861, 1887 and 1899-1904)
  - Low water survey of the Missouri River, 1882, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous engineering reports (Box 5)
  - Letter Book, 1890-1893 (Box 5)
  - Letter Book, 1893-1896 (Box 5)
  - Computation Book (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
    Photographs of fishing and boating excursions, 1911 and 1913; photographs of his office in the engineering department of the Sanitary District of Chicago; and photos from railroad race involving the Chicago and Alton Railroad, 1900.